And
today's daf is דף כ"ה. daf chaf-hey. We start on the משנה
mishna on in the middle of כ"ד עמוד ב'. chaf-dalet amud-bet. Let's
take a look. Okay, אין מדליקין בשמן שריפה ביום טוב. ein madlikin
b'shemen sreyfah b'yom tov. So we had a nice long discussion about
חנוכה, Chanukah, but now we're back to the major theme about which
oils can be used for שבת. Shabbos. And this משנה, mishna, however,
first talks about something you cannot use for יום טוב. Yom Tov.
The last משנה mishna said you cannot use שמן שריפה shemen sreyfah
on שבת. Shabbos. We didn't exactly know from the משנה mishna what
שמן שריפה shemen sreyfah is. The גמרא Gemara explained that it meant
תרומה טמאה, Terumah Tmeiah, oil of תרומה Terumah that became טמא, tamei,
that has to be burned, it's a מצוה mitzvah to burn it.
So it says there, the last משנה mishna said you don't use
it on שבת. Shabbos. This משנה mishna says you don't use it
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. אין מדליקין בשמן שריפה ביום טוב. ein
madlikin b'shemen sreyfah b'yom tov. רבי
ישמעאל אומר, Rabbi Yishmael omer, and now we go back to שבת
Shabbos issues. רבי ישמעאל אומר אין מדליקין בעיטרן מפני כבוד השבת. Rabbi
Yishmael omer ein madlikin b'itran mipnei kvod hashabat. You cannot use עיטרן,
itran, which is some type of a smelly tar or pitch fuel.
I don't know how they translate it there. Any translation? Tar. There
you go. Because of the honor of שבת, Shabbos, because it'll smell
up your house. Or we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. וחכמים מתירין,
Vachachamim matirin, and the Sages allow it. וכל השמנים, V'chol hashemanim, all
oils: שמן שומשמין, shemen shumshumin, sesame seed oil; שמן אגוזים, shemen egozim,
nut oil; שמן צנונות, shemen tnunot, oil of gourds; שמן דגים, shemen
dagim, oil of fish. רש"י Rashi said some type of, you know,
fish innards.
I don't know why he says innards. I mean, fish oil is...
yeah, anyway. All right. שמן פקועות, shemen pakuot, שמן shemen of some
type of, רש"י Rashi also says this is another type of a
gourd. בעיטרן, B'itran, which is what we said before, that here they
are saying explicitly that's on the allowed list, tar; ובנפט, u'benfat, נפט
nefat is, I think it's just naphtha, right?
Is that how it's translated?
Yeah, I think it's some type, also some type of a tar.
רבי טרפון אומר, Rabbi Tarfon omer, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says אין
מדליקין אלא בשמן זית בלבד. ein madlikin ela b'shemen zayit bilvad. You
can only use olive oil.
Yes?
He translates it as a derivative of
pitch.
That's what I said, tar, pitch, yeah, something of, I don't know
the differences between those two. But some... but yeah. All right. So
now the גמרא Gemara says,
like this is interesting, שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz says this is the first historical
source that describes the production of white naphtha, which was common in
the ancient world and unknown in Europe during the Middle Ages.
Okay, I don't see where it describes the production. It just mentions
it. But okay. Maybe it's the first source that mentions it. מאי
טעמא? Mai taama? Okay, now back to the שמן שריפה. shemen sreyfah.
Why can you not burn שמן שריפה shemen sreyfah on יום טוב?
Yom Tov? So again, this is assuming this is what we said
yesterday, תרומה טמאה, Terumah Tmeiah, why can it not be burned? And
you'll remember yesterday there were two explanations. One is there's really not
a יום טוב Yom Tov problem, it's a שבת Shabbos problem because
if we let you use it on שבת, Shabbos, then because there's
a מצוה mitzvah to burn it, you'll try to tip the candle,
the lamp, in order to speed up the burning, even though it's
a clean burning. And the other, which sounds more from this משנה
mishna that it's underscoring a יום טוב Yom Tov issue, is that
no, the primary concern is not a שבת Shabbos concern, it's a
יום טוב Yom Tov concern. And that's because of what we're about
to say, we said yesterday as well. So let's take a look.
לפי שאין שורפין קדשים ביום טוב. L'fi she'ein sorfin kodshim b'yom tov.
You can't burn invalid קדשים kodshim on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and
this also is קודש, kodesh, holy, it's תרומה, Terumah, and it's not
usable, it's טמא, tamei, you can't burn it. Now, what exactly the
comparison is, we will see, because it's not so clear. But let's
first develop this idea that you do not burn קדשים kodshim on
יום
טוב. Yom Tov. מנא הני מילי? Minani milei? Where do we know
you don't burn קדשים kodshim on יום טוב? Yom Tov? אמר חזקיה
וכן תנא דבי חזקיה, Amar Chizkiyah v'chen tana d'bei Chizkiyah, חזקיה Chizkiyah
taught, and it was also a ברייתא braisa taught in the house
of חזקיה, Chizkiyah, אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says, ולא תותירו
ממנו עד בוקר והנותר ממנו עד בוקר באש תשרופו. V'lo sosiru mimenu
ad boker, v'hanotar mimenu ad boker ba'esh tisrofu. This is a פסוק
pasuk by פסח, Pesach, do not leave anything over till the next
morning, and anything over left up until the next morning you shall
burn in the fire. So why does it have to say עד
בוקר? ad boker? It already said don't leave until the morning.
Why does it say again, and anything left until the morning? It's
a little redundant. מה... Ma... so, שאין תלמוד לומר עד בוקר, she'ein
talmud lomar ad boker, why does it say עד בוקר ad boker
again? בוקר שני ליתן לו בוקר שני לשריפתו. Boker sheni litein lo
boker sheini l'sreyfato. The פסוק pasuk comes to give that there's a
second morning when you burn it. You don't burn it the first
morning, which is פסח Pesach day, יום טוב, Yom Tov, you burn
it the second morning. So don't leave it over till פסח Pesach
morning, till the morning of the 15th, and anything you left over
on the next morning, on the 16th, you should burn it. Okay,
so it showed you you can't burn it on פסח Pesach itself.
Now, why... this is נותר, notar, it's not טמא, tamei, but it's
another form of an invalid sacrifice. Now, why can you not burn
it on יום טוב? Yom Tov? You tell me, it should be
obvious. Why? Because... what? It's still valid? No, it's נותר notar though,
and by פסח Pesach morning it's נותר, notar, right? והנותר ממנו. V'hanotar
mimenu. So why should you not burn נותר notar on פסח Pesach
morning, on יום טוב? Yom Tov?
You can't burn, you can burn only for things that you have
to do on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
Right, it's a מלאכה, melachah, burning, so burning קדשים kodshim is not
something that you're getting, it's not אך אשר יעשה לכל נפש, ach
asher yeiaseh l'chol nefesh, you're not getting any personal benefit from, I
mean, any physical הנאה hana'ah from it. So even though it's doing
some מצוה, mitzvah, it's not allowed on יום טוב, Yom Tov, it's
making a fire not for some type of a physical benefit. Okay,
so that seems pretty straightforward. The obvious problem with the comparison to
burning The obvious problem with the comparison to burning oil that has
to be burnt is if you're allowed to benefit from the burning
of תרומה טמאה, terumah tme'ah, why therefore can you not burn it
and use it for light? You can use normal oil for light,
just because you're also doing a מצוה mitzvah of burning it, you
know, that means that you can now not do it? Why should
that be a problem? Okay, so רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both
more or less ask this question. The גמרא Gemara does not say.
The גמרא Gemara just says, oh, you can't burn קדשים טמאים, kodshim
tme'im, you can't burn תרומה טמאה terumah tme'ah on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, but there you're not using it. Here you are using it,
what's the, why is it not allowed? So there's two answers. The
simplest answer which both רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot put out is,
it's a גזירה. gzeirah. Once you can't do it for burning, you
know, invalid קדשים kodshim on יום טוב Yom Tov in the cases
where you're not benefiting, we don't even allow you to burn תרומה
טמאה terumah tme'ah even though you are benefiting because we wanted to
just keep the whole category off limits. You shouldn't come to, you
know, make some association one to the other, and it's all דרבנן.
drabbanan. Okay, that's an easy explanation. תוספות Tosafot gives a more, you
know, sort of conceptual answer, and he says look, he says you're,
it's true you're deriving benefit, but when you burn תרומה טמאה, terumah
tme'ah, but that's incidental. That's not why you're burning it. You're burning
it because there's a מצוה mitzvah to burn תרומה טמאה. terumah tme'ah.
The תורה Torah just says that when you're doing the מצוה mitzvah
of destroying it, you're allowed to derive incidental benefit. Actually we're going
to see later that you should've said that תרומה טמאה terumah tme'ah
is completely off limits and you have to burn it and not
get any benefit from it. But we learn from a פסוק pasuk
that no, there's a special allowance to derive benefit as you're destroying
it. But since the primary purpose of destroying it is not to
serve your benefit, but it's to do the מצוה mitzvah of destroying
it, therefore it is not allowed on יום טוב. Yom Tov. He
makes an interesting comparison to the discussion of bringing
נדרים ונדבות nedarim unedavot on יום טוב, Yom Tov, which is a
major debate as you know that goes back way, way even, you
know, in the pre-תנאי Tannai period. So he says what's the position
of the one that says it's forbidden? Why can't you bring a
free will קרבן? korban? You're going to eat the meat. So why
can't you שחט shacht it, you know? So he says it's the
same idea, that even though you will eat the meat, its primary
act is an act of bringing the קרבן korban to God. It's
not an act of making meat and, you know, creating meat that
you can use. And therefore even though you will, you will derive
benefit, that's not what the act of שחיטה shechitah that קרבן korban
is. So that's how he explains what is going on here. Again,
it's fascinating the גמרא Gemara does not discuss it. It just says
you don't burn קדשים, kodshim, you don't burn תרומה טמאה terumah tme'ah
even though you will be benefiting from the burning. Yes.
So isn't a חגיגה Chagigah offering on יום טוב Yom Tov kind
of a free will offering?
Isn't a חגיגה—yeah, Chagigah but that's a commanded one. When it says
וחגתם אתו חג לה׳, vechagosem oso chag la-Shem, you know, that's the
bringing of the קרבן חגיגה, korban Chagigah, right. But this is one
that you have no particular relationship to יום טוב Yom Tov itself.
So now the גמרא Gemara will continue with other דרשות drashot that
you do not burn קדשים kodshim on יום טוב, Yom Tov, but
again without directly connecting the logic to why that means you don't
burn תרומה terumah on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So let's keep on
going. געזונטהייט. Gezuntheit. So it says אביי Abaye אמר amar אמר קרא
amar kra the פסוק pasuk says עולת שבת בשבתו, olas Shabbos beshabbaso,
the עולה olah of שבת Shabbos in its שבת, Shabbos, ולא עולת
חול בשבת, velo olas chol beShabbos, and not the עולה olah of
the weekday on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, ולא עולת חול ביום טוב, velo
olas chol beYom Tov, not only that, even a weekday קרבן korban
cannot be burned on יום טוב, Yom Tov, the remaining remainder part
of the קרבן. korban. Now how do you know, it says בשבתו,
beshabbaso, how do you know it means not יום טוב? Yom Tov?
So תוספות Tosafot quotes there's another דרשה drashah that says that says
that the בשבתו beshabbaso is a little redundant and coming to include
even another, or actually another דרשה drashah is, sorry, what does תוספות
Tosafot say?
געזונטהייט. Gezuntheit. Anyway תוספות Tosafot says that based on another דרשה drashah
somehow we're able to learn out that this is also including יום
טוב. Yom Tov. That an עולת חול olas chol cannot be on
שבת Shabbos and an עולת חול olas chol cannot be on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. So that shows you that even though you're doing
a מצוה mitzvah of burning קדשים, kodshim, and here it's not even
קדשים טמאים, kodshim tme'im, it's actually legitimate קדשים, kodshim, it's just the
burning of the fats and the portions of the קרבנות. korbanot. Nevertheless,
if it's not a מצוה mitzvah to be done on this שבת
Shabbos or even this יום טוב Yom Tov itself, it cannot be
done. So the same way you can't burn the fats of קדשים
kodshim on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you cannot burn certainly קדשים טמאים
kodshim tme'im on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, so that's that פסוק.
pasuk. רבא Rava אמר רבא amar Rava, says another פסוק. pasuk. אמר
קרא amar kra the פסוק pasuk says הוא לבדו יעשה לכם, hu
levado yeaseh lachem, that which shall be eaten for all people, אשר
יאכל לכל נפש, asher yeachel lechol nefesh, that alone can be done
for you on יום טוב. Yom Tov. הוא hu ולא מכשירין. velo
machshirin. You can only actually do the act of creating food on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, not something that is a making of the
tools for creating food, meaning I cannot create a שחיטה shechitah knife
or sharpen a שחיטה shechitah knife on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay,
I can do something that's directly part of making the food, but
not something that is one stage removed and is about making the
tools that will then let me make the food. That's one thing
we learn out. ולבדו, ulevado, and alone what do we learn out?
ולא מילה שלא בזמנה, velo milah shelo bizmanah, not something that is
like, you know, again what that has to do with food,
only
food related. Is allowed on שבת, Shabbos, it's allowed on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, but שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano where it doesn't have to
be today, that you do not do it even on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. ואתי בקל וחומר. v'asya b'kal vachomer. Now some have a
question whether we have those words. How do we know that, meaning
why do I need a פסוק pasuk to tell me don't
do it שלא בזמנו? shelo bizmano? Why would I have thought you
could do it שלא בזמנו? shelo bizmano? So רש"י Rashi says I
would have made a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. What's the קל וחומר?
kal vachomer? So here's the
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If a כהן kohen has צרעת, tzara'as, you
cannot cut away the צרעת tzara'as in order to allow him to
do the עבודה. avoda. So if it's a competition then between צרעת
tzara'as and doing the עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
then צרעת tzara'as wins. Now עבודה avoda can be done, עבודה avoda
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash can be done on שבת. Shabbos.
So in a competition, this is the transitive axiom of inequality. So
in a competition between עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and שבת, Shabbos, okay, so עבודה avoda wins. So if עבודה avoda
is stronger than שבת Shabbos and צרעת tzara'as is stronger than עבודה,
avoda, so צרעת tzara'as is stronger than שבת. Shabbos. You with me?
Now when you have a מצוה mitzvah of ברית מילה bris milah
and there happens to be צרעת tzara'as on the ערלה, orlah, ברית
מילה bris milah wins and you cut away the צרעת. tzara'as. So
ברית מילה bris milah is stronger than צרעת, tzara'as, which is stronger
than עבודה, avoda, which is stronger than שבת, Shabbos, so ברית מילה
bris milah is stronger than עבודה, avoda, even ברית מילה שלא בזמנו
bris milah shelo bizmano you would cut away the צרעת. tzara'as. So
I would have thought based on that whole transitive axiom of inequality
that you could have cut, that you could have done it on,
you know, maybe שבת, Shabbos, maybe יום טוב, Yom Tov, etc. That's
why I need a פסוק pasuk to tell you not. תוספות Tosafos
says the whole thing isn't a קל וחומר kal vachomer because the
reason you don't do the עבודה avoda when you have צרעת tzara'as
is not because that the צרעת tzara'as is more strong than the
עבודה. avoda. It's just that the person, the כהן kohen who's got
צרעת tzara'as is invalid. It's not like it's not what, פסול pasul
to do the עבודה avoda and it's right and it's not like
this is a greater constraint or whatever, it's that it's not directly
competing with the עבודה, avoda, it's just anyway. So תוספות Tosafos says
there other reasons I would have maybe thought that you could have
done a ברית מילה שלא בזמנו bris milah shelo bizmano on יום
טוב Yom Tov at least and we learn from this פסוק pasuk
that you cannot. But the basic point is, the point being about
all of these is that even things that are somehow מצוה mitzvah
related, you do not do them on יום טוב Yom Tov even
though the act might normally in other circumstances be allowed. You can
normally burn food on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can, I mean
cook food, you can use the fire, you can cut things on
יום טוב Yom Tov even if it's what do you call it
like even like you know if a ברית מילה bris milah is
learned from the prohibition, is learned like a type of a same
prohibition of making a wound and שחיטה, shechita, you can do שחיטה
shechita on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But even though these acts are
permitted in other contexts, they're not permitted to do מצוות mitzvos on
יום טוב Yom Tov that can be done on a different day.
So you can't burn נותר, nosar, you can't burn the fats of
the קרבנות korbanos even though that may be by the next day
will be נותר, nosar, but it's not specifically related to יום טוב.
Yom Tov. You can't do a מילה שלא בזמנו. milah shelo bizmano.
So similarly you cannot burn קדשים kodoshim and if you can't burn
קדשים kodoshim you cannot burn תרומה טמאה. terumah temei'ah. That is the
argument. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says,
שבתון, shabbaton, it says that it is a שבתון, shabbaton, a day
of rest, this is by יום טוב. Yom Tov. It calls יום
טוב Yom Tov a שבתון. shabbaton. עשה, asei, so יום טוב Yom
Tov is not only a negative prohibition, it's also a positive מצוה
mitzvah of
שבתון. shabbaton. והוי ליה יום טוב עשה ולא תעשה. v'havei lei Yom
Tov asei v'lo sa'asei. So יום טוב Yom Tov has a positive
מצוה, mitzvah, שבתון, shabbaton, and a negative, לא תעשה כל מלאכה, lo
sa'asei kol melacha, not to do work. So those two, ואין עשה
דוחה לא תעשה ועשה, v'ein asei docheh lo sa'asei v'asei, the positive
מצוה mitzvah of burning קרבנות, korbanos, of burning נותר באש תשרפו, nosar
ba'eish tisareifu, invalid קרבנות, korbanos, does not override the positive and negative
מצוה mitzvah of יום טוב. Yom Tov. So it's very simple. This
is not something needed for, like I said, for human benefit and
therefore the positive מצוה mitzvah of יום טוב Yom Tov does not
over, the positive מצוה mitzvah of burning קרבנות korbanos does not override
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, ואין עשה דוחה לא תעשה ועשה ביום
טוב הוא דאסור. v'ein asei docheh lo sa'asei v'asei b'Yom Tov hu
d'assur. Now okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is going to go
on. So anyway as we said, all of these are different ways
of saying even though this is a מצוה, mitzvah, it does not,
it's not דוחה docheh יום טוב. Yom Tov. Similarly you don't burn
תרומה טמאה terumah temei'ah on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But again that's
the huge jump. What do you mean the similarly, תרומה טמאה terumah
temei'ah is coming to you know serve my purpose, I'm using it
for light. So as I said, two explanations. רש"י Rashi says or
תוספות, Tosafos, either it's גזירה, gezeirah, what you can't do in other
קדשים kodoshim you cannot do תרומה טמאה. terumah temei'ah. And the other
answer as תוספות Tosafos says is although you're deriving benefit of light,
that is only allowed as an incidental side benefit of the מצוה
mitzvah of burning it. Fundamentally what you have to relate to this
תרומה טמאה terumah temei'ah as invalid תרומה terumah which you have a
מצוה mitzvah to burn and doing the burning directly is not allowed.
The benefit you get is only something that is allowed incidentally. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Let's take a look. It says,
so the גמרא Gemara says יום טוב הוא דאסר, Yom Tov hu
de-asar, so you're telling me you don't burn this on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. הא בחול שפיר דמי. ha be-chol shapir dami. In the
weekday it's okay. What's okay? Meaning in the weekday it's okay to
burn תרומה טמאה trumah tme'ah and to benefit from the light. Right,
that's implicit. We wouldn't have even thought you could do it on
יום טוב Yom Tov if you couldn't benefit from the light. So,
or at least that seems to be the case. Anyway, so how
do you know what we've been, I've been giving you as a
pro- like an assumption to the point taken for granted until now,
that you can benefit from the light? How do you know you
can do it when you're burning תרומה? trumah? So by the way,
the fact that the גמרא Gemara needs to know how do you
know you can do it means that it takes as an assumption
that I would have assumed that תרומה טמאה trumah tme'ah is not
only אסור באכילה asur ba-achilah but also אסור בהנאה. asur ba-hana'ah. Why
I would have assumed that תרומה טמאה trumah tme'ah is אסור בהנאה
asur ba-hana'ah is not clear. There's a long תוספות Tosafot that tries
to figure that out. There are other types of things that are
קדשים kodshim that are invalid that are אסור בהנאה, asur ba-hana'ah, or
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni that's invalid that's אסור, asur, ביכורים bikkurim that's
אסור, asur, but can those serve as good comparisons? There's a תוספות
Tosafot that figures that out. But the גמרא Gemara is assuming if
you have something that has קדושה kedushah like תרומה trumah and it
becomes טמא, tameh, presumably it's אסור בהנאה. asur ba-hana'ah. And therefore how
do I know that when you're destroying it you are allowed this
incidental benefit of benefiting from the light or from the heat? So
how do I know? So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
אמר רב, Amar Rav, כשם שמצוה לשרוף את הקדשים שנטמאו כך מצוה
לשרוף את התרומה שנטמאה. Keshem she-mitzvah lisrof et ha-kodshim she-nitme'u kach mitzvah
lisrof et ha-trumah she-nitme'ah. The same way there's a מצוה mitzvah to
burn קדשים kodshim that became טמא, tameh, there's a מצוה mitzvah to
burn תרומה trumah that became טמא. tameh. Okay, so first thing he's
telling us is that it's a מצוה. mitzvah. It's not just a
way of getting rid of it. You're actually doing a מצוה mitzvah
by burning it. דאמרה תורה, de-amarah Torah, and the תורה Torah says,
בשעת ביעורה תהני, be-sha'at bi'urah tehani, when you are destroying it you
are allowed to derive benefit ממנה, mimmennah, you can derive benefit from
it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says very reasonably, היכן אמרה תורה,
hechan amrah Torah, where did the תורה Torah say this? So מדרב
נחמן, mi-de-Rav Nachman, from what we learned from רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
דאמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר קרא, de-amar Rav Nachman
amar Rabbah bar Avuha amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says, ואני הנה
נתתי לך את משמרת תרומתי, Va-ani hineh natatti lecha et mishmeret trumotai,
I have given you the guarding of my תרומות trumot in the
plural. בשתי תרומות הכתוב מדבר, bi-shtei trumot ha-katuv medaber, talking about two
תרומות trumot that you are guarding. אחת תרומה טהורה ואחת תרומה טמאה,
achat trumah tehorah v'achat trumah tme'ah, you have to protect טהורה tehorah
תרומה trumah and you have to protect טמאה tme'ah תרומה. trumah. So
what do you, how do you protect טהורה tehorah תרומה? trumah? You
make sure it does not become טמא. tameh. How do you protect
טמאה tme'ah תרומה? trumah? You make sure you dispose of it in
the proper way. You don't leave it lying around so you don't
come to eat from it. So therefore in this context we're referring
to also the disposal of טמאה tme'ah תרומה. trumah. And therefore what
does the פסוק pasuk say? And it says
ואמר רחמנא, v'amar Rachmana, and the תורה Torah says לך, lecha, ואני
נתתי לך, va-ani natatti lecha, it shall be for you. שלך תהא
להסיקה תחת תבשילך, shelcha teheh le-hasika tachat tavshilcha, you can benefit from
it even when we're talking about תרומה טמאה. trumah tme'ah. So when
you are guarding the תרומה טמאה, trumah tme'ah, guarding it from being
eaten, which means you're destroying it, so when you are burning and
destroying the תרומה טמאה, trumah tme'ah, לך, lecha, you are allowed incidentally
to derive benefit from that burning of it. You can use it
to make a fire for cooking by or to get the light
from. So here we learn a couple of major principles about תרומה
טמאה. trumah tme'ah. Number one is it's אסור בהנאה. asur ba-hana'ah. The
גמרא Gemara doesn't demonstrate that, it assumes it. Number two is there's
a מצוה mitzvah to burn it, which it says by analogy to
קדשים. kodshim. Number three though, based on this פסוק pasuk of משמרת
תרומתי mishmeret trumotai and לך, lecha, when you are burning it and
when you are destroying it you can incidentally derive benefit. And as
תוספות Tosafot explains, because that is only something you're allowed to do
incidentally when you are doing the primary responsibility of burning it, therefore
you cannot do it on יום טוב Yom Tov because it's not
being done for the sake of deriving benefit. Fundamentally what you have
to do is destroy it. Now there's an interesting debate of רש"י
Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, what this mean, how we know there's a
מצוה mitzvah to burn it. The גמרא Gemara just says like קדשים.
kodshim. So how much do we mean that like קדשים? kodshim? So
if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says the
very first narrow line of רש"י, Rashi,
it's a תרומה שנטמאה. trumah she-nitme'ah. רש"י Rashi says דדמיא לקודש, di-dmya
le-kodesh, first it's similar to קדשים, kodshim, so there's a מצוה mitzvah
to burn קדשים. kodshim. ועוד משום תקלה, v'od mishum takalah, also we
don't want you to, it shouldn't be a stumbling block, we don't
want you to accidentally eat it. So the second one seems completely
rabbinic. We gotta get it out of the way, we don't want
you to accidentally eat it, and therefore you have a מצוה mitzvah
to burn it. The first one seems to be more of an
argument like really by analogy to קדשים kodshim and maybe there's even
a biblical מצוה mitzvah to burn it. So תוספות Tosafot raises this
question whether there is actually a biblical מצוה mitzvah to burn it.
Even if you said there was a biblical responsibility to avoid accidentally
eating it, like from the פסוק pasuk of משמרת תרומתי, mishmeret trumotai,
guard my תרומה, trumah, that would not say it's a מצוה mitzvah
to burn it and you could bury it, you could dispose of
it otherwise. So whether it's really a
מצוה mitzvah sort of seems to go both, suggest both ways and
תוספות Tosafot also debates whether it really is a biblical מצוה mitzvah
to burn it. I should say that the גמרא Gemara also has
another possibility of how
you
So that would be a way of getting rid of it and
then also allowing you some incidental benefit. So you see that you
don't have to only burn it. Of course, you could say something
that's able to be burnt, like oil, has to be burnt. Something
that's not able to be burnt, like wine, you have to destroy
it in whatever way you can best destroy it. But this does
leave to this question about whether this is a biblical מצוה mitzvah
of burning it, but certainly we're understanding that however you destroy it,
the תורה Torah is telling you you have to destroy it and
that you can derive incidental benefit when you do destroy it. Yes.
That high alcohol wine they had in Talmudic times, oh
maybe it would have burnt? That's an interesting question.
I don't know, I don't know, for the best as I know
the גמרא Gemara does not discuss ever burning wine. What?
Can you cook with it?
Can you cook with No, because then you are actually then you're
like eating it. Yeah right right, no. The idea is to destroy
it, it's an act of of, you know, of its destruction where
you're benefiting in the process of it being destroyed. Right. Cooking is
an act of like using heat to prepare something, not to destroy
something.
I guess it's an interesting question about let's say you were destroying
it like they're talking here, let's say you burnt the wine and
the flavors got absorbed in some food, you know, the flavors of
the steam off of the wine? Put it on the... I'm not
so sure why that would be so different than the air freshener
where you're right, you're getting the smell let's from that wine? So
yeah, it's interesting this idea that you can derive benefit except that
comes through the process of destroy. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara now
continues another דרשה, drasha, ואיבעית אימא ve-iba'it eima what you can get
benefit incidentally from destroying the תרומה טמאה, truma t'meya, מדרב אשי mi-Rav
Ashi מדרב
אבוהו, mi-Rav Avohu, from רב אבוהו. Rav Avohu. דאמר רב אבוהו אמר
רבי יוחנן De-amar Rav Avohu amar Rabbi Yochanan ולא ביערתי ממנו בטמא,
velo bi'arti mimenu be-tamey, this is the וידוי vidui that a person
says by מעשר, ma'aser, מעשר
שני, ma'aser sheni, I did not destroy from it when I was
טמא. tamey.
So what is ביערתי ממנו? bi'arti mimenu? Meaning when either I was
טמא tamey or it was טמא. tamey. So by מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni you say, I did not sort of destroy it בטומאה be-tumah
meaning and benefit from it when I when when in the destruction.
So ממנו אי אתה מבעיר. mimenu i ata mav'ir. From it, from
מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, you cannot destroy when it is טמא. tamey.
אבל אתה מבעיר שמן של תרומה שנטמאת, aval ata mav'ir shemen shel
truma she-nitmet, but you can destroy you know תרומה, truma, oil of
תרומה truma that became טמאה. t'meya. Now presumably you destroy and benefit
because presumably what you are testifying to by the מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni in this וידוי vidui is that you did not derive improper
benefit. So you did not eat it when you were טמא tamey
or you did not benefit from it when it was טמא. tamey.
So that's by מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, but by something else, like
by תרומה, truma, you can derive benefit when you destroy it and
it is טמאה. t'meya. So the גמרא Gemara says
so that's another דרשה. drasha. Of course how do you know that
it's דווקא davka תרומה truma that's by contrast, we'll see anyway in
a second in the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא
ממנו אי אתה מבעיר אבל אתה מבעיר שמן של קודש שנטמא, ve-eima
mimenu i ata mav'ir aval ata mav'ir shemen shel kodesh she-nitma, how
do you know that the contrast is to is to תרומה, truma,
maybe the contrast is to שמן של קרבנות, shemen shel korbanot, of
like a מנחה. mincha. Maybe when you destroy a קרבן korban you
should be or at least oil you should be allowed to derive
benefit. I just realized something by the way, that by the תרומה
truma it says שמן של תרומה שנטמאת shemen shel truma she-nitmet and
by the שמן shemen it says שמן של קודש שנטמא. shemen shel
kodesh she-nitma. So the word שנטמאת she-nitmet and שנטמא she-nitma is not
going on the word שמן, shemen, it's going on the word תרומה
truma or קודש. kodesh. Right? You see the point? שמן של תרומה
שנטמאת shemen shel truma she-nitmet or שמן של קודש שנטמא, shemen shel
kodesh she-nitma, which is interesting because presumably it's the oil that's becoming
טמא. tamey. But okay, either way. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
לאו קל וחומר הוא, lav kal vachomer hu, one minute, that would
be a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. מה מעשר הקל, ma ma'aser ha-kal,
if מעשר ma'aser which is much less weighty than קרבנות, korbanot, than
קדשים, kodashim, אמרה תורה לא ביערתי ממנו בטמא, amra Torah lo bi'arti
mimenu be-tamey, you cannot get benefit when you burn it and it's
טמא, tamey, קודש חמור, kodesh chamur, קרבנות korbanot which are so much
more weighty, לא כל שכן, lo kol sheken, how much more so
should you not? So the גמרא Gemara says if that's what you're
saying, אי הכי, ei hachi, you're saying that a קל וחומר kal
vachomer for מעשר, ma'aser, so תרומה נמי תיתי בקל וחומר, truma nami
titi be-kal vachomer, so תרומה truma also should be more weighty than
מעשר. ma'aser. Right? So the גמרא Gemara so you know תרומה truma
is קודש, kodesh, can only be eaten by a כהן, kohen, can't
be eaten by a זר. zar. So if you had to make
a list of how weighty the different things are, קרבנות korbanot would
be on the top, קדשים kodashim would be on the top, then
תרומה, truma, then מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. And if מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni can't be derived benefit when it's טמא tamey and you're destroying
it, it should the same way it should be a קל וחומר
kal vachomer by קודש, kodesh, by שמן shemen of קרבנות, korbanot, it
should also be a קל וחומר kal vachomer by תרומה. truma. So
the גמרא Gemara says well we gotta pick one, so we'd rather
pick the one that we're going to allow as the one that
is less strict of of between קרבנות korbanot and תרומה. truma. It's
true you've got a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, they really all should
be אסור, assur, but if the פסוק pasuk is teaching us that
one is allowed, then it's going to be the one that's less
weighty and תרומה truma is less weighty than קרבנות. korbanot. So let's
take a look. גמרא Gemara says הכתיב ממנו, haksiv mimenu, no, you're
right, both of them should be אסור assur by a קל וחומר,
kal vachomer, but from the ממנו mimenu we learn that one is
allowed. ומה ראית, u'mah ra-ita, what made you think that תרומה trumah
is the more lenient one that we should allow it more than
oil of קרבנות? korbanot? מסתברא קודש לא ממעטינן. mistavra kodesh lo mematina.
It makes sense we're not going to limit קודש kodesh from and
meaning to allow you to benefit from קודש kodesh when you burn
it. Why? שכן פנ"ק עכ"ס, shekein Panak Akas, there you go. Now
we're going to spell it out. So what are they? פ pay
is פיגול, piggul, like קרבנות korbanot can become פיגול, piggul, you have
a thought seated at the wrong time in the wrong place, it's
an איסור כרת issur karet to eat that type it's an איסור
לאו issur lav to have the thought it's איסור כרת issur karet
eat the קרבן korban that was שחט shechted with that thought in
mind that applies only to קרבנות, korbanot, not to תרומה, trumah, not
to מעשר. ma'aser. נותר, notar, if you leave it over a day
or whatever it's past its time then there's a כרת karet prohibition
of eating the leftover meat also only by קרבנות. korbanot. That's the
נ. nun. ק kuf is קרבן, korban, which is it's called a
קרבן, korban, okay, which basically means that clearly right, but that seems
that that itself is a weighty just categorization even without a particular
נפקא מינה, nafka mina, it's just a little funny. Let me just
double check רש"י, Rashi I don't think רש"י, Rashi, yeah, yeah רש"י
Rashi, doesn't say anything other than it's called a קרבן. korban. The
ע ayin here is not for is really from the מ"ע, mem
ayin, מעילה, Me'ila, presumably they picked the ע ayin because it was
easier for the סימן. siman. There's a prohibition of מעילה Me'ila which
we learned a whole מסכת masechet of that if it's prohibited to
derive benefit and you transgress a לאו lav and you bring a
קרבן korban if you derive improper
benefit. וכרת vekaret is the כ, kaf, if you eat from a
קרבן korban and you're not allowed to eat from it then you
get כרת. karet. If you're a זר zar or something of that
nature. אסור לאונן assur lo-onen and the ס samekh is אסור לאונן,
assur lo-onen, okay, the ס samekh could be pretty generic, but okay
it would be harder to say עכ"ס akas yes. Anyway, if somebody
is a has a death that and the on that day and
the body had not been buried they cannot eat קרבנות korbanot and
again that does not apply to תרומה. trumah. Okay, so those are
the special categories of קרבן, korban, all these are weightier than תרומה,
trumah, קרבן korban is clearly more severe. ק kuf for קרבן korban
is
yeah is there a preference for six element mnemonics because I
think oh that's a good question. Could be also because it creates
a like just greater weight like פנ"ק עכ"ס Panak Akas is like
is it that could be, that's a nice point. There's also other
things that haven't been mentioned here like תוספות Tosafot says, which is
קרבנות korbanot can become טמא, tamei, can become a רביעי לטומאה revii
le'tumah in a way that even more residual טומאה tumah can make
a קרבן korban טמא. tamei. If somebody is a טבול יום, tvul
yom, they you know someone excuse me is מחוסר כפורים, mechusar kippurim,
it's been nighttime since they gone to the מקוה mikvah but they
haven't finished the טהרה taharah process by bringing a קרבן korban the
next morning, they can eat תרומה, trumah, they can't eat a קרבן.
korban. So there are other things that could have been listed, yes.
But it's איסור
כרת issur karet for a זר zar to eat תרומה. trumah. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to get to that. It's actually not
איסור כרת, issur karet, it's actually an איסור מיתה בידי שמים issur
misah bidei shamayim and that raises interesting question which is worse of
those two? Okay, I wouldn't want either of them, which is worse?
So let's take a look. So that's the six ways in which
קרבנות korbanot are more serious. So the גמרא Gemara says אדרבה, adarabba,
תרומה לא ממעטינן, trumah lo mematina, let's not exclude תרומה. trumah. תרומה
trumah is weightier than קרבנות. korbanot. Why? שכן מחפ"ז סימן. shekein Machpaz
siman. Four things. מיתה, misah, so you get מיתה בידי שמים misah
bidei shamayim if a non-כהן kohen eats תרומה. trumah. חומש, chomesh, you
have to add a חומש chomesh if the זר zar eats תרומה
trumah in you know then they have to give it back and
they add a חומש. chomesh. It's actually interesting because that's somewhat similar
to the מעילה, Me'ila, so רש"י Rashi discusses some of the differences
between the זרים zarim between the חומש chomesh of the תרומה trumah
and the מעילה Me'ila by a קרבן, korban, but they are different.
ואין לה פדיון, v'ein la pidyon, you cannot redeem תרומה. trumah. You
can redeem a קרבן korban that got a blemish. There's no way
you can transfer the קדושה kedusha of a קרבן. korban. ואסור לזרים,
ve'assur le'zarim, and it cannot be eaten to non-כהנים kohanim whereas קרבנות
korbanot at least some קרבנות korbanot can be eaten by non-כהנים. kohanim.
שלמים shelamim are you know תודה todah and so on, so whereas
all תרומה trumah is forbidden. So anyway, so תרומה trumah has things
which is weightier than a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara says
הנך נפישן. hanach nefishen. Alright but six beats out four. Alright, so
קרבנות korbanot still are weightier than תרומה. trumah. ואיבעית אימא v'ibayis eima
if you want I can tell you חמור chamur it's still bottom
line is
קודש חמור, kodesh chamur, קדשים kodshim is more חמור chamur from the
simple fact that what שכן ענוש כרת. shekein onosh karet. כרת karet
is worse than מיתה בידי שמים. misah bidei shamayim. Now why is
כרת karet worse than מיתה בידי שמים? misah bidei shamayim? What are
their differences? So רש"י Rashi says כרת karet means that a person
dies before his appointed time and childless. Whereas מיתה בידי שמים misah
bidei shamayim means a person just dies before their appointed time but
not childless. תוספות Tosafot is a whole big תוספות Tosafot here, do
you want to see how big it is? Turn to page כ"ח.
kaf chet. That tries to figure out the differences between כרת karet
and מיתה בידי שמים misah bidei shamayim and gives a couple of
other answers.
He says once you have children you can't be punished with כרת
karet anymore.
Well חס ושלום chas veshalom but I mean you know but they...
die, I mean, to try, you die without children, not never having
had children. That's the idea. So תוספות Tosfos says no, that there's
actually sometimes the תורה Torah says כרת וערירי Kares V'ariri and ערירי,
Ariri, and ערירי Ariri means childless. So כרת Kares by itself does
not mean childless. So he says כרת Kares means, based on another
גמרא, Gemara, that a person dies before they're sixty. מיתה בידי שמים,
Misa Bidei Shamayim, he says, is not telling you when you die.
A person could live their whole life, but it somehow means that
the death is seen as attributable to this sin. So it's a
little bit different. It's not necessarily saying that, or you die before
your appointed time, but not necessarily before sixty. So a lot of
different possibilities here about what is כרת Kares as opposed to מיתה
בידי שמים. Misa Bidei Shamayim. But anyway, clearly the גמרא Gemara concludes
that כרת, Kares, whatever it is, is worse. As I said, either
it means without children or it means, you know, before sixty. Anyway,
various interpretations of כרת Kares that it's somehow more severe than מיתה
בידי שמים. Misa Bidei Shamayim. Now the גמרא Gemara just wraps this
up. So that was another דרשה. drasha. All of that was a
דרשה drasha of how I know you can derive benefit from תרומה
Terumah because you cannot derive benefit from מעשר Maaser when you're destroying
it, מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. And something is excluded and something implicitly
is allowed. So we have to allow something. We'd rather say that
תרומה Terumah is what's being allowed than קרבנות. Korbanot. That's why we
had that דרשה, drasha, but there you know another דרשה drasha that
you can derive benefit from תרומה Terumah when you destroy it. Let's
just read the very last דרשה drasha at the top of כה
עמוד ב׳. Chaf-Hey Amud Beis. רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak אמר קרא, amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says, תתן לו. titen
lo. It says ראשית דגנך תירשך ויצהרך תתן לו. Reishis degancha tiroshcha
viyitzharecha titen lo. You shall give
him. לו ולא לאורו. lo velo l'oro. So he when you give
him good תרומה, Terumah, תרומה טהורה, Terumah Tehorah, he should use it
for himself and not burn it. מכלל דבת אורה הוא. mikhlal de-vas
orah hu. So if the תורה Torah has to exclude that, don't
burn תרומה Terumah and use it for firewood, if it is טהור,
tahor, you can infer that if it is טמא, tamei, you can
burn it and use it for firewood, which is pretty funny because
it's basically reading, you know, totally reading into the פסוק. pasuk. The
פסוק pasuk doesn't say לו ולא לאורו. lo velo l'oro. That was
the rabbis that read the ולא לאורו velo l'oro and then they
read back out what they had read into it a minute ago.
So תוספות Tosfos asks that question. But anyway, that's one final דרשה.
drasha. Yes, Joe?
On the question of כרת, Kares, do any commentators see it as
more of a metaphysical kind of punishment than this is the, you
know, the consequences that we can view in this world rather than,
you know, the idea of being cut off from your people? Right.
So the
פשט הפסוקים, pshat hapsukim, it's not so clear. On the one hand,
the פסוקים psukim say ונכרתה הנפש ההיא, vinikhras hanefesh hahi, so it
speaks about נפש, nefesh, which makes us think about like metaphysical soul,
although נפש nefesh very often is used in the sense of person.
Like כל הנפש אשר לא תעונה בעצם היום הזה ונכרתה. kol hanefesh
asher lo se'une b'etzem hayom hazeh vinikhrasoh. That's a perfect example. A
נפש nefesh is being נכרתה, nikhrasoh, but the נפש nefesh is the
one that's not fasting, right? So it doesn't just mean your metaphysical
soul. It means you're not fasting. Right?
So therefore, I believe that the אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra says and,
you know, certainly the פשט הפסוקים pshat hapsukim is that it just
means you are cut off from your people. That maybe it's some
type of like excommunication, you know, or maybe, but it does not
necessarily refer to some, you know, your metaphysical soul is cut off
or that you die before your time. But at what stage does
it get that meaning? That I don't have the answer to. But
in terms of the פשט הפסוקים, pshat hapsukim, you are correct. It
is certainly quite possible. Which by the way also explains, you know,
the two מצוות עשה mitzvot aseh that you get כרת Kares for,
which is מילה Milah and קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, are both מצוות
mitzvot that are about identity. You know, being identified as part of
the people. מילה Milah for men and פסח Pesach for everyone. You
know, sort of part enacting that fundamental foundational historical narrative. So if
you're not participating in that, then you are נכרת. nikhras. You know,
actually just this week's פרשה parsha by לך לך. Lech Lecha. But
you're right. פשט הפסוקים pshat hapsukim is not necessarily talking about early
death or something metaphysical.
So it is interesting to try to see when that exactly occurred
and how that, you know, and how the מיתה בידי שמים, Misa
Bidei Shamayim, which might, I mean what's the פסוק pasuk by, how
do we know it's מיתה בידי שמים Misa Bidei Shamayim anyway?
What does the פסוק pasuk say? We know it's not literal מיתה.
misa. It's not so clear. Sometimes it says ומתו בו כי יחללהו.
umesu vo ki yichaliluhu. It's not so clear from the פסוקים psukim
always that it means מיתה בידי שמים Misa Bidei Shamayim when חז״ל
Chazal say that's what it means. Anyway, but that is a very
good point. Okay, so now we continue. So that is about שרפה,
srefah, burning תרומה טמאה Terumah Tmeah on יום טוב, Yom Tov, which
for some reason is a problem as a, anyway, either it's גזירה
gezeira אטולי דקדשים atuli d'kodshim or as תוספות Tosfos says, it is
because fundamentally you're not doing it for benefit. It's only incidental. And
because you can't do it on יום טוב, Yom Tov, one way
of reading yesterday is therefore, when it says you don't burn it
ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, it means ערב שבת Erev Shabbos that happened
to be a יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now we go to the
next part of the משנה Mishnah and back to שבת. Shabbos. You
cannot use this נפט, neft, this type of a pitch or tar,
because of כבוד שבת kavod Shabbos according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
and the חכמים Chachamim disagree. So מאי טעמא? mai taama? What's the
concern of כבוד שבת? kavod Shabbos? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so says
רבא. Rava מתוך שריחו
רע mitoch she-rei'o ra has such a bad smell, גזירה שמא יניחנה
ויצא. gezeirah shema yanichenah ve-yetze. You'll leave the room, you don't want
to be in the room where this thing is burning. אמר ליה
אביי, Amar lei Abaye, ויצא? ve-yetze? So leave the room! Meaning according
to, so according to אביי, Abaye, the only concern of the oils
is, what's the concern of the bad oils and the bad wicks?
You will come to fiddle with it. So if it's got a
bad smell, you're not going to fiddle with it, you'll just leave
the room. Now you could say maybe you'll extinguish it. So fine,
so say you'll maybe you'll extinguish it. But if the whole concern
is you'll leave the room, why do I have to care about
that? It's, you're not going to come to be מחלל שבת. mechalel
Shabbat. So אמר amar רבא, Rava. so as so, the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, no, שאני
אומר, sh'ani omer, because I say, הדלקת נר בשבת חובה. hadlakas ner
bi-Shabbat hovah. There's an obligation to have candles on שבת. Shabbat. So
here is what I mentioned to you in the משנה, Mishnah, it
never says explicitly you have a חיוב hiyuv to have candles. What
it does say is, well, that you cannot use certain oils and
wicks because we're afraid it'll lead to חילול שבת. hillul Shabbat. Does
that mean that there is a מצוה mitzvah or not? You know,
maybe not, maybe you're just lighting it because you need light in
your house on שבת. Shabbat. But here we have that it says
חובה. hovah. Now if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות
Tosafot says הדלקת נר בשבת חובה. hadlakas ner bi-Shabbat hovah. He says,
פירוש במקום סעודה. perush bimkom se'udah. The חידוש hiddush here of אביי
Abaye
is that there's a מצוה mitzvah? to have it lit where you're
eating. So we don't want you to leave and eat in a
room that you don't have light. How do I make, how do
I know he's emphasizing eating? דחובה הוא שישה במקום הנר משום עונג,
de-hovah hu she-yishe bimkom ha-ner mishum oneg, because that increases your עונג
שבת. oneg Shabbat. You know, eating in darkness is not so pleasurable.
אבל מהדלקת נר גופיה לא הוי פרך אביי. aval me-hadlakas ner gufei
lo havei parikh Abaye. From the idea of just lighting, nobody doubted
that lighting was an obligation. How do you know that? דפשיטא
דחובה היא דתנן בפרקין להלן משנה, de-pashita de-hovah hi de-tnan be-varkin le-halan
mishnah, על שלש עבירות נשים מתות בשעת לידתן על שאינן זהירות בהדלקת
הנר. al shalosh aveirot nashim metot be-sha'at leidatan al she-einan zehirot be-hadlakas
ha-ner. That if women are getting punished according to this משנה Mishnah
for not being careful in candle lighting, it sounds like we're talking
about a ritual act. It sounds like we're not just talking about
making sure there are lights on in the house on שבת. Shabbat.
So this as I said is a big question. When did candle
lighting become a מצוה? mitzvah. Again, it's not explicit in the משנה.
Mishnah. You could infer from the fact as תוספות Tosafot does that
there's a consequence for not being careful about it, that you're, that
you're punished, that you're punished for not doing a מצוה. mitzvah But
you know, the מצוה mitzvah could be again that it's still a
little bit shy of saying that it's a ritual act. Though you
know, let's say it said, women are punished for not making, making
sure there's good hot food for שבת. Shabbat. Okay, that's also a
מצוה mitzvah of כבוד שבת kavod Shabbat and עונג שבת. oneg Shabbat.
It doesn't mean that the act of making food becomes ritualized. It
means part of כבוד kavod and עונג שבת oneg Shabbat is that
you have light, you have food and so on. So it's not
so clear how that begins to turn into a ritual, but תוספות
Tosafot says at least there's a sense that it's, it's something that
needs to be done. What's being added here is, is that it
needs to be done where you eat, you don't want to walk
out from the place that you're eating. Of course it's not so
clear the גמרא Gemara here mentions eating. You could have said, if
you're walking out of every room that this is burning in, then
you're not achieving the point of having light where you need there
to be light, where you need to be living. But anyway רש"י,
Rashi I also didn't mention רש"י. Rashi, רש"י Rashi. and תוספות Tosafot
both say that the problem here is, is that it's not, if
you're lighting it where you're eating and then you're going to be
forced to eat where there's no light. And there אביי Abaye is
saying, I say that part of the מצוה mitzvah. of candle lighting
is that there be light where you eat. And therefore you have
to use something that does not have this bad smell. Yes, רבקה?
Rivka?
Why do you think they wanted to terrify people into being religious?
About the women dying?
Like that story we had with the woman running around? Right. Giving
a, and the answer was.
So I'm not sure they wanted to terrify people. I would ask
that we leave that discussion, I know, no, no. The משנה Mishnah
about women dying, right.
No, but this one too, you eat the תרומה, terumah, the כרת
kares attached to that.
That's the תורה! Torah! The תורה Torah has all these punishments for
sinning.
To eating שמן שריפה. shemen sereifah. No, no, no.
No, no, no. The כרת kares is only if you eat, no,
no, no. That was learned to say, no, no, no. That was
just a general point that תרומה terumah is, whether תרומה terumah or
קדש kodesh is weightier. That you get כרת kares is only if
you eat תרומה terumah when you are טמא, tamei, or if you're
a non כהן kohen or so on. But that's a, not a
question for the גמרא. Gemara. The תורה Torah has all of these
very weighty punishments. Right, left and right, everybody's being put to death
or getting כרת kares and so on. So let's wait for the
discussion about the women dying when we get to that משנה, Mishnah,
if we could. Okay, because that's mentioned by תוספות. Tosafot.
Right, people dying
for.
I
understand. All right, look, let's, let's hold off that discussion till we
get to the later משנה. Mishnah. That's not really the topic here.
Okay, so yes.
I'm not sure I understand where the eating is coming from. What?
I don't
see where the eating is coming from.
So right, it's not in the גמרא. Gemara. רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosfos both introduced it. I don't know why they had introduced it.
I mean as long as you're not benefiting from the light, then
you're not if there's an obligation. The obligation is to have light
where you need it. So if you lit it in rooms that
you need to be in and now you can't be in that
room because it smells, but for whatever reason רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosfos both assumed that the problem here is that you're leaving the
room where you wanted to be eating and that's the problem. Okay,
but this certainly adds a level of the sense of what is
your obligation of candle lighting. But again let's keep on going as
we discuss how much is this become a actual ritual and a
מעשה מצוה. ma'aseh mitzvah. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, דאמר
רב נחמן בר רב זבדא ואמרי לה אמר רב נחמן בר רב
אמר רב הדלקת נר בשבת חובה. De'amar Rav Nachman bar Rav Zavda
ve'amrei lah amar Rav Nachman bar Rav amar Rav hadlakat ner beShabbat
chovah. Lighting candles on Shabbat is an obligation. ורחיצת ידים ורגלים בחמין
ערבית רשות. Verichitzat yadayim veraglayim bechamin aravit reshut. Washing your taking a
nice hot shower, literally washing your hands and face with hot water
on ערב שבת Erev Shabbat רשות reshut is permissible, meaning you don't
have to, it's not as obligatory as making sure that there's light
in the house on Shabbat is taking a nice hot bath or
shower ערב שבת Erev Shabbat for כבוד שבת. kavod Shabbat. So אמר
רב, amar Rav, so ואני אומר מצוה ve'ani omer mitzvah that no,
actually taking a nice hot shower is a מצוה. mitzvah It's not
just a רשות reshut to get it's a מצוה mitzvah? of כבוד
שבת. kavod Shabbat. מאי מצוה? mai mitzvah? What's the מצוה? mitzvah דאמר
רב יהודה אמר רב כך היה מנהגו של רבי יהודה בר אלעאי.
De'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav kach hayah minhago shel Rabi Yehuda bar
Elai. This was the מנהג minhag of רבי יהודה בר אלעאי, Rabi
Yehuda bar Elai, the standard רבי יהודה. Rabi Yehuda. ערב שבת מביאים
לו עריבה מלאה חמין. Erev Shabbat mevi'im lo arivah mele'ah chamin. ערב
שבת Erev Shabbat they would bring him a, you know sort of
a bucket filled with hot water. ורוחץ פניו ידיו ורגליו. Verocheitz panav
yadav veraglav. He would wash his face, his hands, and his feet,
note to get himself ready for Shabbat. ומתעטף ויושב בסדינים המצוייצים. Umit'ateif
veyosheiv bisdinim hamtzuyatzim. And he would sit and he would wrap himself
with linen garments that had ציצית tzitzit on them. ודומה למלאך ה'
צבאות. Vedomeh lemalach Hashem Tzeva'ot. He was similar to an heavenly angel
of God. So here's this idea of sort of like preparing yourself
in holiness for Shabbat. I have to tell you, you know, even
if I've, you know, taken a shower that morning and it's a
short Shabbat and I really haven't gotten a chance to get sweated
up or whatever, taking a shower like right ערב שבת Erev Shabbat
really puts you in a very different mood. You're preparing for Shabbat,
you're nice, you're clean, you put on these nice clothes. So that's
an idea of entering Shabbat with a certain degree of holiness. It
is interesting though that image because you could have just said that
כבוד kavod is being clean, you know? So the same way you
clean your house and you spread your table and you wear nice
clothes, you take a shower, you get you get clean. Why it
said מאי מצוה mai mitzvah and had to give this example and
this very like, you know, nice image of looking like a, you
know, looking like an angel is not exactly clear, you know, why
it didn't just say a more sort of prosaic aspect of just
getting ready. But maybe the I don't know, maybe again this idea
of doing it like right before Shabbat is the point. So now
the גמרא Gemara goes on a little digression about this. It says,
והיו תלמידיו מחבים ממנו כנפי כסותן. Vehayu talmidav mechabim mimeno kanfei kesutan.
His students would hide the corners of their garments, which did not
have ציצית tzitzit on them. Why did their garments not have ציצית?
tzitzit? Because he's wearing a linen garment. And the linen garment, if
you want to have תכלת, techelet, not just the white strings, but
תכלת, techelet, תכלת techelet can only be of wool. So he would
actually make כלאים, kilayim, שעטנז, shatnez, but that's allowed if there's no
other way if you're wearing a linen garment, you have a מצוה
mitzvah of ציצית, tzitzit, a מצוה mitzvah of תכלת, techelet, that overrides
עשה דוחה לא תעשה aseh docheh lo ta'aseh and you could have
שעטנז shatnez in your ציצית tzitzit if you have to because of
the wool תכלת techelet and the linen garment. But the students did
not do that. They did not put תכלת techelet in their ציצית.
tzitzit. Maybe they didn't put any ציצית tzitzit on or maybe they
only had the linen strings but they didn't have the תכלת. techelet.
So they hid their corners of their garments from him. אמר להן,
amar lahen, he said to them, בני, banai, my students, my children,
לא כך שניתי לכם, lo kach shaniti lachem, haven't I not told
you? סדין בציצית. Sadin betzitzit. If you have linen in your garments
regarding ציצית, tzitzit, בית שמאי פוטרין, Beit Shammai potrin, and בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says it's exempt from תכלת, techelet, ובית הלל מחייבין, uBeit
Hillel mechayivin, and בית הלל Beit Hillel obligate it. והלכה כדברי בית
הלל. Vehalacha kedivrei Beit Hillel. We rule like בית הלל. Beit Hillel.
ואינהו סברי בהא. Ve'inhu savri beha. But they hold by this גזרה
משום כסות לילה. gezeira mishum kesut lailah. Even if in theory we
hold like בית הלל, Beit Hillel, we don't put the wool strings
because you might come to do it by night garments. And since
night garments are not obligated in ציצית, tzitzit, so therefore, and therefore
it would really be שעטנז. shatnez. So although technically שעטנז shatnez is
allowed here, you're playing with fire because you might do it in
another context where it's not a real מצוה mitzvah, and then you
would come to transgress the prohibition of שעטנז. shatnez. So we do
not have תכלת. techelet. So that's the way תוספות Tosfos reads it.
תוספות Tosfos reads it that they would have linen strings, they just
wouldn't have the תכלת techelet string. And תוספות Tosfos actually says and
then the question is, is that how does בית שמאי Beit Shammai
hold? תוספות Tosfos says that really בית שמאי Beit Shammai also agrees
in principle you're allowed to have תכלת, techelet, you know, that ציצית
tzitzit overrides שעטנז. shatnez. But I'm sorry not בית הלל, בית שמאי.
בית שמאי Beit Shammai holds that in principle you're allowed to have
תכלת. techelet. But בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you don't do it
because it would could lead to doing שעטנז שלא במקום מצוה, shatnez
shelo bimkom mitzvah, that actually this is one of the places where
we rule like בית שמאי Beit Shammai over בית הלל. Beit Hillel.
רש"י Rashi has another read which is that רש"י Rashi has another
read which is that they actually had no ציצית tzitzis in their
garments, which is even more shocking. Why not at least put linen
strings in? Okay, but anyway, that's a little bit of an interesting
digression, talking about him wrapping himself in this linen garment. Now, going
back to this issue about
candlelighting as a מצוה, mitzvah. notice that the phrase the גמרא Gemara
used by candlelighting was חובה, chovah, whereas when it talked about sort
of bathing it said מצוה. mitzvah מצוה mitzvah. to us sounds like
a more ritual type of an act as opposed to something you
gotta do, you gotta make sure there's hot water, you gotta make
sure there's this, you gotta make sure there's that, it's not so
much as like a religious
connotation to it. So there are times where the גמרא Gemara contrasts
חובה chovah to מצוה. mitzvah. One very famous case is where it
speaks about מים אחרונים mayim acharonim is חובה chovah and מים ראשונים
mayim rishonim is מצוה. mitzvah And the question is what is meant
by that contrast? So in one place, this is in חולין, Chullin,
תוספות Tosafos says that חובה chovah means it's more of an obligation.
Since מים אחרונים mayim acharonim is about, you know that the salt
can damage your eyes and it's a health issue, so it's a
health issue, it's more weighty than the מים ראשונים mayim rishonim which
is a מצוה mitzvah, but not a health issue. So one way
of understanding חובה chovah is greater obligation. But another way of understanding
חובה chovah is, and these aren't contradictory, is that it's not so
much about a מצוה, mitzvah it's about health, and therefore you don't
make a ברכה bracha on מים אחרונים, mayim acharonim, you do make
a ברכה bracha on מים ראשונים. mayim rishonim. Okay, so those two
aspects, מצוה mitzvah has, you know, חובה chovah might mean more weighty,
but it also means less of a מצוה mitzvah feel to it.
So the question is what does it mean here when it says
נר שבת חובה. ner shabbos chovah. On the one hand you could
say it means that it's more weighty. We said before that נר
שבת ner shabbos overrides a קידוש, kiddush, right, because it's so important
to have שלום בית shalom bayis and so on. But you could
also say maybe like we've been saying, maybe it's not so clear
that there's this ritual act of lighting, maybe it's just you gotta
make sure that there's light in the house on שבת shabbos and
light where you're eating and all these types of things. You know
you want to have עונג שבת, oneg shabbos, but maybe it's not
so much of a ritual act. And this leads to this big
question which is how much, when did we ritualize the act of
lighting candles? Not just having light, but the act of lighting candles,
when did we begin making the ברכה? bracha? You do not have
the ברכה bracha in the גמרא, Gemara, the ברכה bracha began at
the Geonic period, and תוספות Tosafos here records, and we'll just look
for a minute this debate between two of the בעלי תוספות, Baalei
Tosafos, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam and רבינו משולם. Rabbeinu Meshullam. So if
you take a look at תוספות חובה, Tosafos chovah, he says like
this.
Oh, just ויש שרוצים, v'yesh she'rotzim, actually
let's first read the first line. חובה: לגבי רחיצת ידים בחמים קרי
ליה חובה. chovah: legabei rechitzas yadayim be'chamim kerei lei chovah. Compared to
getting taking that hot bath or shower ערב שבת, erev shabbos, it's
a חובה, chovah, דלא הוי כל כך מצוה, de'lo havei kol kach
mitzvah, meaning חובה chovah it means it does not have so much
of a מצוה mitzvah. religious context to it, a ritual aspect. So
it's funny, if you ask which is more ritualized,
lighting candles or taking the shower, obviously you'd say lighting candles, but
maybe not yet in the גמרא. Gemara. So then he says if
you skip down like five lines, beginning of the line, ויש שרוצים
לומר דאין לברך על הדלקת נר. v'yesh she'rotzim lomar de'ein l'vareich al
hadlakas ner. You shouldn't make a ברכה bracha on lighting candles, מדקרי
ליה חובה. mide'karei lei chovah. It's an obligation but it doesn't mean
it's a מצוה. mitzvah, דאמרינן מים אחרונים חובה ואין טעונים ברכה, de'amrinan
mayim acharonim chovah ve'ein te'unim bracha, like מים אחרונים mayim acharonim it's
just called a חובה, chovah, which might mean it's weighty, but it
also means that it's not a ritual act and you don't make
a ברכה. bracha. ואמר רבינו תם דשיבוש הוא, ve'amar Rabbeinu Tam de'shibush
hu, that is a mistake. דלא דמי למים אחרונים דלא הוי אלא
להצלה בעלמא. de'lo dami l'mayim acharonim d'lo havei ela le'hatzala b'alma. מים
אחרונים mayim acharonim is only about health. אבל הדלקת נר היא חובה
של מצות עונג שבת. aval hadlakas ner hi chovah shel mitzvas oneg
shabbos.
It's an obligation of a מצוה, mitzvah, it is a מצוה, מצות
עונג שבת. mitzvas oneg shabbos. וכמה חובות הן דטעונים ברכה. ve'kamma chovos
hen detunim bracha.
And there are many obligations that require ברכה. bracha. And then he
goes on to say another interesting debate. This is actually a whole
back and forth in תשובות רבינו תם teshuvos Rabbeinu Tam and תשובות
ספר הישר teshuvos sefer hayashar between רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam and I
believe ספר משולם, Sefer Meshullam, which is let's say the lights are
already on ערב שבת. erev shabbos. Are you supposed to turn them
off and relight them? So רבינו משולם Rabbeinu Meshullam says no, the
whole point, there's no ritual act of lighting, the whole point is
having light in your house on שבת. shabbos. So if your lights
are on from ערב שבת, erev shabbos, you leave your lights on.
It's just about having light. And רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says first
he says maybe you're right, but even so, and then he says
no you're supposed to turn them off and light them again. There
is an act, a ritual act of lighting. Not mentioned anywhere in
the גמרא, Gemara, but the once we start making a ברכה bracha
on this, which begins in the Geonic period, that it becomes to
be understood as an actual ritual מעשה מצוה ma'aseh mitzvah and not
just having the light but actually doing the lighting. Okay, and that
really is you know is interesting you see how it sort of
the basis of that is in the גמרא Gemara but it really
crystallizes later. Okay,
so now back to the גמרא, Gemara, we end with this with
some אגדתא. agaddata. ותזנח משלום נפשי נשיתי טובה. vattiznach mishalom nafshi nishisi
tova. Quoting a פסוק pasuk from איכה. Eicha. My soul has been
abandoned from from peace, I have forgotten all goodness. מאי ותזנח משלום
נפשי? mai vattiznach mishalom nafshi? What does this mean? אמר רבי אבהו
זו הדלקת נר בשבת. amar Rabbi Abahu zu hadlakas ner b'shabbos. If
you don't have the candles lit on שבת, shabbos, you don't have
any peace, you're walking around in the darkness, you're stumbling over the
furniture, you're... eating in darkness, it's not שלום בית. Shalom Bayit. נשיתי
טובה, Nashiti Tova, I forgot good. What is that? That's something else.
So אמרי רבי ירמיה, Amrei Rabbi Yirmeya, זו בית המרחץ. zu beit
hamerchatz. That is the bathhouse, right? Remember we've had a whole discussion
before about how important bathhouses are. Presumably, now again, that—does that mean
for שבת? Shabbat? Or does that mean in general that you don't
have an opportunity to use a bathhouse? Not clear. The גמרא Gemara
then continues and it says,
where were we? Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן
אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, זו רחיצת ידים ורגלים בחמין. zu rechitzat yadayim
veraglayim bechamin. This is washing your hands and face in hot water,
which we mentioned before about ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. But again here,
because it's talking about you lost something that gives you goodness, presumably
it means just in general. You go around without cleanliness, that's נשיתי
טובה. Nashiti Tova. רבי יצחק נפחא אומר, Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha omer, זו
מטה נאה וכלים נאים. zu mitah na'ah vechelim na'im. It's having like,
you know, nice furnishings, nice vessels in the home. It's a sense
of peace of mind when, you know, things look nice and everything
is, you know, pleasant. So that's—that's what it's referring to. This is
interesting, like what creates that psychological state of being at peace, you
know? Cleanliness, light obviously is critical and so on. שעליה, She'aleha, nice—the
nice vessels on it, meaning like nice dishes. רבי אבא אומר, Rabbi
Abba omer, again, some of this could be read specifically in the
שבת Shabbat context, so if we're talking about bathing and having a
nice table and nice dishes, although it also says a nice bed.
But it seems to be not limited to שבת, Shabbat, general this
idea of what does it mean to be in a state of
peace and goodness as opposed to not. רבי אבא אומר, Rabbi Abba
omer, זו מטה מוצעת, zu mitah mutza'at, a made bed, ואישה מקושטת,
veishah mekushetet, and an adorned woman, לתלמידי חכמים, letalmidei chachamim, for the
Torah sages. So I don't know exactly what to make of that.
First of all, the difference between מטה מוצעת mitah mutza'at and מטה
נאה. mitah na'ah. מטה נאה Mitah na'ah presumably means like it's just
nice furnishings, whereas מטה מוצעת mitah mutza'at means somebody's made your bed,
like the wife has made your bed, and אישה מקושטת. ishah mekushetet.
So also this emphasis of לתלמידי חכמים. letalmidei chachamim. But obviously this
גמרא Gemara is a little bit problematic in the sort of objectifying
of the woman together with the bed, and specifically something for Torah
sages. I really don't know what to make of that. So we
were on that point, yes.
I saw רש"י Rashi saying worthy and suitable for—Yeah, I saw that.
That was a nice little apologetic there.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. נשיתי טובה. Nashiti Tova.
Is this a play on the word?
Oh, נשיתי Nashiti and נשים. Nashim. Oh, I hadn't thought about that.
That's a nice idea. That's for the last one. Oh, maybe the
others—I wouldn't think about it, but maybe it's נאה שעליה, na'eh she'aleha,
מטה נאה, mitah na'ah, כלים נאים שעליה, keilim na'im she'aleha, נשיתי. Nashiti.
Hmm, I hadn't thought about that. Doesn't work for the earlier ones,
does it? בית המרחץ, Beit hamerchatz, I can't see that. רחיצת ידים
ורגלים. Rechitzat yadayim veraglayim. But maybe the נאה שעליה na'eh she'aleha and
אישה מקושטת ishah mekushetet and מטה, mitah, that's a nice point. That's
a nice
point. Okay. So תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. איזהו עשיר? Eizehu ashir? Now
that we're talking about what it means to sort of, you know,
have a—be a state of goodness and pleasantness and peace, so similar
talking about like what is the state to be working to achieve.
איזהו עשיר, Eizehu ashir, who is a rich person? כל שיש לו
נחת רוח בעשרו, kol sheyesh lo nachat ruach be'oshro, דברי רבי מאיר.
divrei Rabbi Meir. Whoever has satisfaction with his wealth. This is what
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. So רש"י Rashi identifies this with the
famous line in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, which is השמח בחלקו. hasame'ach
bechelko. But the מהרש"א Maharsha says, I don't think so, because it
doesn't say חלקו, chelko, it says בעשרו. be'oshro. So he actually says
that some people can be very wealthy and not satisfied, right? אוהב
כסף לא ישבע כסף. Ohev kesef lo yisba kesef.
And other people, you know, yes, it's not enough what רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is saying, is to having a lot of—having a lot
of possessions does not make you happy. What makes you happy is
that you are satisfied with what you have. So in a way,
it's similar to השמח בחלקו, hasame'ach bechelko, but he's saying even maybe
it is having a lot, but having a lot and being satisfied
with it. Now the גמרא Gemara gives other
explanations. סימן מ-ת-ק-ש siman Mem-Tav-Kuf-Shin or different people we're going to be
quoting. רבי טרפון אומר. Rabbi Tarfon omer, מ Mem is רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. ת Tav is טרפון. Tarfon. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon אומר,
omer. כל שיש לו ק' כרמים ומאה שדות וק' עבדים שעובדים
בהם. kol sheyesh lo kuf kramim u'me'ah sadot ve'kuf avadim she'ovdim bahem.
You want to know what rich is? Rich is having millions and
millions of dollars. Okay, so having a hundred
vineyards and a hundred fields and a hundred slaves working on them.
Now רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, by the way, was very wealthy. So
it's not so—so surprising that he's explaining it in very concrete terms.
רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, the מהרש"א Maharsha I think tries
to take the edge off of that a little bit and say
that he's trying to sort of also sort of hint to the
idea of אוהב כסף לא ישבע כסף ohev kesef lo yisba kesef
and like, you know, the more you have, the more you want,
and you'll never get happy this way. But anyway, not so clear,
okay? רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, which is the ק, Kuf,
כל
שיש לו אישה נאה במעשים. kol sheyesh lo ishah na'ah bema'asim. So
here we similar to the אישה נאה, ishah na'ah, but here connecting
it not to peace or, you know, goodness, but to wealth. And
again, thinking about רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, right, רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's
wife and the whole story about his wife, who's the one that
told him to forget about the money and to go and to
become a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. So how— Having a wife, from
obviously from the male perspective, having a wife who has good deeds
and is a proper character, that makes a person, a man wealthy.
He also says
מרבה נכסים מרבה דאגה. marbeh nechasim marbeh de'agah.
Oh, he maybe even said מרבה נכסים מרבה דאגה. marbeh nechasim marbeh
de'agah. That's interesting too. But Rabbi Yose says כל שיש לו בית
הכסא סמוך לשולחנו. kol sheyesh lo beis hakiseh samuch l'shulchano. Okay, we
had similar comments to this before. If you have your bathroom closest,
especially when you didn't have indoor plumbing. Now Rabbi Yose also was
actually known to have had gastrointestinal problems. So again, it's very interesting
the way some of these statements might be reflecting their own personal
situation. תניא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Tanya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. So
that was a nice little digression. Are we already over? Let's just
read one more line. אין מדליקין בצרי. ein madlikin b'tzari. You cannot
use בצרי. b'tzari. Right, הצרי אין בגלעד? hatzari ein b'gilad? Right, צרי
tzari is some type of very aromatic type of a balsam oil.
So you cannot use it. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why not? אמר
רבה, Amar Rabbah, מתוך שריחו נודף, mitoch sh'reicho nodef, גזרה שמא יסתפק
ממנו. gezeirah shema yistapek mimenu. It smells so fragrant that they say,
ooh, that smells so good, let me try to dip my bread
into the oil there. And then by dipping your bread in the
oil, you're removing the oil from the flame, and that is מכבה.
mechabeh. You're causing the flame to extinguish before its time, and that
would be a מלאכה. melachah. So we'll continue with this tomorrow.
And then they call balsam that is not the same plant as...